We're going to make a little
Python program that can tell us what
operating system we have, what computer
we have, and what that computer has.  Okay,
so for that,
to 002 and information from my
punpython computer.
So I'm going to build a little
program over here.  Let's do it
quickly.  Let's see.  and create a small
program in Python that one tells me
what operating system I'm on and two, provides me with
all the
possible information
about my system.
Three, a
report that is
readable by anyone
and four that is multiplatform.
Well, it got away from me.  Okay, so
let's dump that program.
Now we will execute it and from there
we will see.
And from there we will execute to
check what we have.
Okay, let's see.  Oh, okay.  Okay,
come on, wait a minute.
And here, okay, let's see it.  I'm going to put
a little program here.  Well,
small, maybe not so small, but
okay.  Milk.
Well, I expected it to be small,
but it's not small, but oh well, that's
okay.  You'll have it there to
run.
Come on, go on.  Oh.  Wow,
damn it.  Okay, information from
my computer.  And now,
just like before, what I'm going to
do is go to
computer systems first, in this
case, operating system installation
and exercises, and I'm going to run that
Python file.  So Python 30002.
And it tells me this, right?  and he tells me
, let's see, let's see.   He
tells me that this system, this program,
I insist, will
not only be encrypted, but will give us
that information in a structure that is difficult to
read, okay, for a
human being.  But well, it's a Linux system,
eh, with the kernel, with the 6.14 kernel,
whatever, such platform, right?  The
Mac network ID, which has nothing to do
with Apple.  is this one here and the
Python path is this one.  Okay, I have a
processor of this architecture
with 16 logical cores, 10 physical cores,
running at 2736,
minimum 400, maximum 4475,
okay?  And CPU usage right now, right
now it's at 23%, okay?  RAM.  In
this case I have 16 GB available.  I have
5.5 available.  I used 7.6, which
means, I don't know, let's see.
But hey, I've used 66%
of the RAM right now.  Okay, what discs do I have?
Well, I have these disks, they have
this memory, these are used, I have
this network, I have the users, okay?  And
if you want more detail, then install
this.  But of course, this is for Linux,
obviously,
and it has to work for
all platforms.  Okay?  So
this gives us a perspective of what
the computer system I'm on
right now has.  Because?  Well, because
when I develop
computer applications, what I just
did will be very necessary to know
the environment in which
those computer programs will run.
Okay, I'm going to close here and let's go
to subunit two, which is functions of
an operating system.  Here you are going to
help me, so I'll create a new file 001
functions.python
and tell me what functions
an operating system has.
What are you telling me?
Many of you know them.
functions of an operating system.
Okay,
okay.  Interpret
human inputs
and therefore offer outputs
to the human.  That is, input is
done
through the keyboard and mouse and
output is done through the screen,
speakers, and
printer, classically.  Okay, keyboard,
mouse, microphone, it can also be an
input,
okay?  One of them is this.
Very good.  Another is to manage
processes and programs.
Very good.  What else?
Programs generate files, right?   They
generate what are called files and
directories, folders, right?  Well, they
also manage
the file system
where
both programs
and documents are stored, right?  Like the
documents that
the programs generate or work with, right?  What else?
Although this is the bulk of what
an operating system does,
right?  manage the hardware.
[Music]
In principle, in principle we could
say that there is little more.  Okay, fine.
Types of operating systems.  Then, if
necessary, we will expand this list.
Types of operating systems.  Of course, the
typologies
can vary, okay?  I more than types,
because of course, types according to what
ordering criterion.  Well, the
main current operating systems
on the desktop
are Windows, obviously,
MacOS
and Linux.  With what, with what
frequency difference?  Well, stat counter
global stats
is a statistics page that I
like quite a bit for this.  So I'm
going to see
operating system only desktop
region.  Okay, let's take Spain
ah or P
Spain
and I want it from
January 2009 to August 2025.
And what we see is this here, okay?
What we see is that Windows is still the
majority.
Little by little it is going down.
OSX, which is the purple line.
Little by little it has been rising over
the decades, it seems that little by
little Apple is eating away at its
market share, but it is still far from that
60-something percent.
Linux is very low.  Linux on
desktop operating systems has a
very low share.  Okay?  So
Windows is the majority
in slow decline.
Macos
is a minority.
This is a
minority
but
slowly growing and Linux on desktop,
in desktop environments is very much a
minority.
Okay?  In mobile environments we
obviously have Android and iOS.
So I come to edit the graph
and now I want mobile.  If you want,
let's leave the tablet topic aside for a bit,
okay?  Tablets, unfortunately, have
not had the success that was expected
of them, but well,
Google arrived a little late
to the market, but when it arrived it ate up
the entire market share.  75%.
75%.
Eh, iOS came first, but then I had to
compete, so I got 25%
of the market share.  And then we have
very minority systems, right?
We had Simbian, but obviously,
in the end, the ones that have remained in
the market are, as you know, Android
and iOS, right?  And then we have
server operating systems,
meaning the desktop is
the machine that your users are going to be using to
view applications.
mobiles,
the mobiles with which they will see your
applications if they are optimized for
it
or applications or web applications.  And
operating systems on the server are the
server where
your applications will be hosted.
What is the current fee?  Well,
we have Linux with approximately
70% and we have Windows Server with,
well, 30% or so.  Years ago,
Apple also had the Mac OS Server,
but then they removed it from the market
because they couldn't, let's say, handle that market
share.  So I'm going to say GPT chat, I'm going
to say
server-side OS share.
Let's see it.
Of course, it depends a lot on how you define the
server.  Okay, very good.  It's true.
Let's see.  Linux has it, let's see.
Oh, look, Linux has approximately
62.7, that is, mixing everything,
putting everything there in a barrech, but
okay, I like it.  Good.  I 60
and 2.7%.7%.
Okay, so Windows Server has
a, let's see.
Well, and the rest is gone for
Windows and such.  Let's see this
here.
Okay.  And server, server
server.
Yeah, but
server
no
server,
right?  For example, well, look, depending on
who you ask, they might say
88% and Windows 11.
Okay, so, let's put 80 and 20.
So, what happens?  Well, on
the desktop, obviously, we have to know Windows, but we also have to know that there are a lot of people using macOS, so we might need to have some way to test our programs on macOS or to test our websites on macOS.  to see how they
look, because the point is not that you publish
a website and that's it, the point is that you
then have to see how people will see it.
In terms of mobile, yes, Android is
75%, but a 25% market share
is not insignificant.
And in terms of servers, well, 80% of the
time you'll end up using a
Linux server, but Windows Servers
also have a 20%
market share, which means that it
's also important to
know, well, all these
operating systems.
Okay, let's wrap things up today.  We are going to
finish today.  I'm going to skip
unit four a bit.  We will talk about types of
applications,
licenses, and types of licenses.
Which two licenses?  001 types of
pund licenses.
What two types of licenses do
you think exist in
operating systems?  What do you say?
There are two main types:
proprietary licenses
and free software licenses.
Proprietary licenses that are
effectively closed software, right?
Which are specific to Windows and Mac OS.
and Unix, etc., and the
free software licenses that apply to other
operating systems such as Linux,
Free BSD and similar ones.
At this point, of course, with
proprietary licenses,
I'm going to do what
none of you have ever done, which is a
Windows license,
right?  Windows License.
Okay, let's see.  It is the legal permission.
Microsoft Windows, licensing resources
,
license terms.  Let's see,
okay?  Microsoft Software License Terms
,
OK?  And here are the
terms that govern use, what you can
do and what you can't do with a
Microsoft license, with a
Windows license.  Okay?  Okay.  I'm going to
copy it here, I'm going to paste it.
You've been using Windows your whole life,
and I'll bet you
've never even read the operating system license
.
MacOS user license.
Nobody does.  Nobody does.  Okay,
so
legal,
Mac software license agreement for the Mac Pro. But wait
a minute, I don't want external pages,
I want a
software license agreement.
Software license agreements.  Come on,
there are licenses.  Now, Macosta Taho,
for example, or Mac Server, okay?
Whatever.  Mao, who is the last one, and I do this,
okay?  and I stick it to myself.
Macos
Windows,
okay?  And here we have the license terms
that I'm going to see if they continue to
include.  By the way, it's 895 little pages
of nothing.  I mean, theoretically before
using a Mac you have to have read
this legal agreement for Okay, there's a
part, let's see if they still put it, right?
Let's see, let's
see.
And here, here, here, here.
Okay.  Okay.  Okay.
Well, it says you
can't deploy
Apple apps for systems related to
air traffic control, life support,
or weapons systems.
Okay, there was a little note here years ago
in the
license agreement, at least in 2010, which is that it
prevented you from using a Mac if you were going
to use it to develop weapons
of mass destruction, which you said,
well, I hadn't thought about that, but it's
good to know.  Okay?  Good.  And then,
what is the license for Windows, for
Linux, sorry?  Well, it's the GPL license.
The GPL license is here.  Come on, here
it is.  Okay, onto licenses, and just a
moment here,
public license in HTML format.
Okay, so when do you use free software
or when you, well, who would use a Mac
to make machines of
mass destruction or to make weapons of
mass destruction?  Technically, any
computer can be used to make
a weapon of mass destruction.  Why
not?  I mean,
if someone likes Mac and is comfortable in
that environment, I don't see why not.  That is,
you can do the same thing with Windows,
Mac, or Linux.  Okay, so this is the
GPL3 license.
So, from here on, it
's important that you start
reading these licenses because no, but
no, not necessarily a Linux or a Windows
is better than a Mac for making a weapon.
In the end it's the same.  In the end, at
a programmer level, they really do
exactly the same thing.  At a
user level, there will be people who
prefer Windows, Mac, or Linux, but at a
programmer level,
you can really program and implement with any of the three,
and you can do whatever you
want.
So, the idea is this and with this I
end today's class, which is the
next one.
You are going to make software.  Right now
we're learning, we're taking
the first steps and right now the
only thing you're worried about,
let's say, is learning how to program, okay?
learn to program, how the
language works and all that, but later on,
when you finish software, when you finish
programs, you will want to launch them, you
will want to communicate them, you will want to
publish them and when that moment comes, that's
when you're going to be interested in knowing the
types of software licenses there are,
because that way you'll be able to know how you
can distribute your programs,
what you have rights to, what obligations
you have.  and have read other
software licenses, as this may be useful to you.  What
I'm showing you are
operating system licenses.
Then there are software licenses,
which are slightly
different, but have a lot in
common, right?  So, since we're
in this section, in this
teaching unit number two on installing
operating systems, that's why I'm
telling you, we're going to read about operating system licenses
and later on,
obviously, we'll talk about
software licenses,
okay?  With this, we'll stop this
subject today, okay?  Because the next
day, installation procedure, then
comes the process of how to install
an operating system step by step.   We'll
use virtualization,
we'll use Virtual Box, which you
've probably used in your intermediate level, and
if not, you'll see how
easy it is to use.  And what we'll do
is install different
operating systems, both Windows and Linux, on the
machine you have, and we'll see how,
thanks to these
virtualization technologies, we can
experiment, we can play, and we can
test different operating systems
within our own computer.
Okay?  Well,